<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-ietf-detnet-controller-plane-framework-15" number="9938" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" consensus="true" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DetNet Controller Plane">A Framework for the Deterministic Networking (DetNet)
    Controller Plane</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9938"/>
    <author fullname="Andrew G. Malis" initials="A." surname="Malis">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <email>agmalis@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Xuesong Geng" initials="X." surname="Geng" role="editor">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <email>gengxuesong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Mach (Guoyi)Chen" initials="M." surname="(Guoyi)Chen">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mach.chen@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Balazs Varga" initials="B." surname="Varga">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <email>balazs.a.varga@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos" initials="CJ." surname="Bernardos">
      <organization abbrev="UC3M">Universidad Carlos III de Madrid</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Av. Universidad, 30</street>
          <city>Leganes, Madrid</city>
	  <code>28911</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+34 91624 6236</phone>
        <email>cjbc@it.uc3m.es</email>
        <uri>http://www.it.uc3m.es/cjbc/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2026"/>
    <area>RTG</area>
    <workgroup>detnet</workgroup>

<keyword>DetNet</keyword>
<keyword>Controller plane</keyword>
<keyword>SDN</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides a framework overview for the Deterministic
      Networking (DetNet) Controller Plane. It discusses concepts and
      requirements for the DetNet Controller Plane, which could be the basis for a future
      solution specification.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Deterministic Networking (DetNet) provides the ability to carry
      specified unicast or multicast data flows for real-time applications
      with extremely low packet loss rates and assured maximum end-to-end
      delivery latency. A description of the general background and concepts
      of DetNet can be found in <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The DetNet data plane is defined in the DetNet data plane framework
      <xref target="RFC8938"/> (and is further explained in the associated DetNet MPLS
      <xref target="RFC8964"/>, the DetNet IP <xref target="RFC8939"/>, and other data plane
      specifications <xref target="RFC9023"/> <xref target="RFC9024"/> <xref target="RFC9025"/> <xref target="RFC9037"/> <xref target="RFC9056"/>).</t>
      <t>Note that in the DetNet overall architecture, the controller plane
      includes what are more usually considered separate control and
      management planes (see <xref target="RFC8655" section="4.4.2"/>). The management plane is primarily
      involved with fault management, configuration management, and performance
      management (sometimes accounting management and security management are
      also considered in the management plane (<xref target="RFC6632" section="4.2"/>) but they are out of the scope of this
      document). At the same time, the control plane is primarily responsible for the
      instantiation and maintenance of flows, MPLS label allocation and
      distribution, and active in-band or out-of-band signaling to support
      DetNet functions. In the DetNet architecture, all of this functionality
      is combined into a single controller plane. See <xref target="RFC8655" section="4.4.2"/> and the aggregation of control and management planes
      in <xref target="RFC7426" format="default"/> for further details.</t>
      <t>While the DetNet architecture and data plane documents are primarily
      concerned with data plane operations, they do contain some requirements and considerations
      for functions that would be required in order to automate DetNet service
      provisioning and monitoring via a DetNet Controller Plane (e.g., see <xref target="RFC8938" section="4"/>). The purpose
      of this document is to take these requirements and considerations into a single document
      and extend and discuss how various possible DetNet Controller Plane architectures
      could be used to satisfy these requirements, while not providing the
      protocol details for a DetNet Controller Plane solution. Such controller
      plane protocol solutions will be the subject of subsequent
      documents. Therefore, this document should be considered as the authoritative reference to be considered if/when protocol work on the DetNet Controller Plane starts.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="requirements" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>DetNet Controller Plane Requirements</name>
      <t>Other DetNet documents, including <xref target="RFC8655"
      format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>, <xref
      target="RFC9551" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC9055"
      format="default"/>, among others, contain requirements for the
      controller plane. For convenience, these requirements have been compiled
      here. These requirements have been organized into three groups: 1)
      requirements primarily applicable to the control plane, 2) requirements
      primarily applicable to the management plane, and 3) requirements
      applicable to both planes. In addition, security requirements for the
      DetNet Controller Plane have been discussed in <xref target="RFC9055"
      format="default"/>, and a summary of those requirements is provided in
      <xref target="requirements-for-both-planes"/>. For the sake of clarity, when applicable, the document in which the requirements originally appear is referenced.</t>
      <section anchor="detnet-control-plane-requirements" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>DetNet Control Plane Requirements</name>
        <t>The primary requirements for the DetNet Control Plane are as follows:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Support the dynamic instantiation, modification, and deletion of
            DetNet flows. This may include some or all of explicit path
            determination, link bandwidth reservations, restriction of flows to
            specific links (e.g., IEEE 802.1 Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN)
            links), node buffer and other resource reservations, specification
            of required queuing disciplines along the path, the ability to manage
            bidirectional flows, etc., as needed for a flow <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Support DetNet flow aggregation and de-aggregation via the
            ability to dynamically create and delete flow aggregates (FAs)
            and modify existing FAs by adding or deleting
            participating flows <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Allow flow instantiation requests to originate in an end
            application (via an Application Programming Interface (API) via
            static provisioning or via a dynamic control plane, such as a
            Software-Defined Networking (SDN) controller or distributed signaling protocols). See
            <xref target="control-plane-architecture" format="default"/> for further discussion
            of these options.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Manage, in the case of the DetNet MPLS data plane, DetNet
            Service Label (S-Label), Forwarding Label (F-Label), and
            Aggregation Label (A-Label) <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/> allocation
            and distribution <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Support, also in the case of the DetNet MPLS data plane, the
            DetNet service sub-layer, which provides DetNet service functions,
            such as protection and reordering through the use of Packet
            Replication, Elimination, and Ordering Functions
            (PREOF) <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Support the queue control techniques defined in 
            <xref target="RFC8655" section="4.5" sectionFormat="comma"/> and <xref target="RFC9320" format="default"/> that require
            time synchronization among the network data plane nodes.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Advertise static and dynamic node and link characteristics, such
            as capabilities and adjacencies to other network nodes (for
            dynamic signaling approaches) or to network controllers (for
            centralized approaches) <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Scale to handle the number of DetNet flows expected in a domain
            (which may require per-flow signaling or provisioning) <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Provision flow identification information at each of the nodes
            along the path. Flow identification may differ depending on the
            location in the network and the DetNet functionality (e.g., transit
            node vs. relay node) <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="detnet-management-plane-requirements" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>DetNet Management Plane Requirements</name>
        <t>The primary requirements for the DetNet management plane are as follows:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Monitor the performance of DetNet flows and nodes to ensure
            that they are meeting required objectives, both proactively and
            on demand <xref target="RFC9551" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Support DetNet flow continuity check and connectivity
            verification functions <xref target="RFC9551" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Support testing and monitoring of packet replication, duplicate
            elimination, and packet ordering functionality in the DetNet
            domain <xref target="RFC9551" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="requirements-for-both-planes" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements for Both Planes</name>
        <t>The following requirements apply to both the DetNet control and
        management planes:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Operate in a converged network domain that contains both DetNet
            and non-DetNet flows <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Adapt to DetNet domain topology changes such as link or node
            failures (fault recovery/restoration), additions, and removals <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>In addition to the above, the DetNet Controller Plane should also satisfy security requirements derived from <xref target="RFC9055" format="default"/>,
   which defines the security framework for DetNet. The following
   requirements are especially relevant:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Integrity and authenticity of control/signaling packets: The controller plane should ensure that signaling and control messages cannot be modified or injected by unauthorized entities and should prevent spoofing and segmentation attacks.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Protection against controller compromise: Mechanisms should exist to verify the legitimacy of controllers and to prevent unauthorized components from impersonating them.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>System-wide security design: The architecture must account for the possibility of compromised nodes or controllers, ensuring resilience so that the failure or subversion of a single component does not cause catastrophic impact.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Timely delivery of control plane messages: The controller plane should ensure that control and signaling messages are delivered without undue delay to prevent disruption of DetNet services without resource leakage.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="control-plane-architecture" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>DetNet Control Plane Architecture</name>
      <t>As noted in the <xref target="introduction" format="title"/>, the DetNet Control Plane is responsible
      for the instantiation and maintenance of flows, the allocation and
      distribution of flow-related information (e.g., MPLS label), and active
      in-band or out-of-band information distribution to support these
      functions.</t>
      <t>The following sections define three types of DetNet Control Plane
      architectures: 1) a fully distributed control plane utilizing dynamic
      signaling protocols, 2) a fully centralized SDN-like control plane, and 3) a
      hybrid control plane containing both distributed protocols and
      centralized controlling. This document describes the various
      information exchanges between entities in the network for each type of
      these architectures and the corresponding advantages and
      disadvantages.</t>
      <t>The examples in the following sections illustrate
      possible mechanisms that could be used in each type of the
      architectures. They are not meant to be exhaustive or to preclude any
      other possible mechanism that could be used in place of those used in
      the examples.</t>
      <section anchor="distributed-control-plane" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Distributed Control Plane and Signaling Protocols</name>
        <t>In a fully distributed configuration model, the User-Network
        Interface (UNI) information is transmitted over a DetNet UNI protocol
        from the user side to the network side. Then, the UNI and network
        configuration information propagates in the network via distributed
        control plane signaling protocols. Such a DetNet UNI protocol is not
        necessary when the end systems are DetNet capable.</t>
        <t>Taking an RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC3209" format="default"/> MPLS network as an example, where end systems are
        not part of the DetNet domain:</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
	  <li>
            <t>Network nodes collect topology information and DetNet
            capabilities of the network nodes through IGP.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>The ingress edge node receives a flow establishment request from
            the UNI and calculates one or more valid paths.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>The ingress node sends a PATH message with an explicit route
            through RSVP-TE. After receiving the PATH
            message, the egress edge node sends a RESV message with the
            distributed label and resource reservation request.</t>
          </li>
        </ol>
        <t> In this example, both the IGP and RSVP-TE may require extensions
        for DetNet.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sdnfully-centralized-control-plane" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Fully Centralized Control Plane</name>
        <t>In the fully centralized configuration model (e.g., using an SDN controller), both flow and UNI
        information can be transmitted from a centralized user controller or from other
        applications, via an API or northbound interface, to a centralized
        controller. Network node configurations for DetNet flows are
        performed by the controller using a protocol such as NETCONF
        <xref target="RFC6241"/>, YANG <xref target="RFC6020"/> <xref target="RFC7950"/>, DetNet YANG <xref target="RFC9633"/>, or a PCE-based central controller (PCE-CC) <xref target="RFC8283"/>.</t>
        <t>Take the following case as an example:</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
	  <li>
            <t>A centralized controller collects topology information and
            DetNet capabilities of the network nodes via NETCONF/YANG.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>The controller receives a flow establishment request from a UNI
            and calculates one or more valid paths through the network.</t>
          </li>	  
          <li>
            <t>The controller chooses the optimal path and configures the
            devices along that path for DetNet flow transmission via
            PCE-CC.</t>
          </li>
        </ol>
        <t>The protocols in the above example may require extensions for
        DetNet.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="combined-control-plane-partly-centralized-partly-distributed" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Hybrid Control Plane (Partly Centralized and Partly Distributed)</name>
        <t>In the hybrid model, the controller and control plane protocols work
        together to provide DetNet services, and there are a number of
        possible combinations.</t>
        <t>In the following case, the RSVP-TE and controller are used
        together:</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
	  <li>
            <t>A controller collects topology information and DetNet
            capabilities of the network nodes via an IGP and/or the Border Gateway Protocol - Link State (BGP-LS) <xref target="RFC9552" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>A controller receives a flow establishment request through API
            and calculates one or more valid paths through the network.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Based on the calculation result, the controller distributes
            flow path information to the ingress edge node and configures
            network nodes along the path with necessary DetNet information
            (e.g., for replication/duplicate elimination).</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Using RSVP-TE, the ingress edge node sends a PATH message with
            an explicit route. After receiving the PATH message, the egress
            edge node sends a RESV message with the distributed label and
            resource reservation request.</t>
          </li>
        </ol>
        <t>There are many other variations that could be included in a hybrid
        control plane. The requested DetNet extensions for a protocol in each
        possible case is for future work.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="detnet-control-plane-additional-details-and-issues" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>DetNet Control Plane for DetNet Mechanisms</name>
      <t>This section discusses the requested control plane features for DetNet
      mechanisms as defined in <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/>, including PREOF. Different DetNet
      services may implement any or all of these based on the requirements.</t>
      <section anchor="explicit-paths" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Explicit Paths</name>
        <t>Explicit paths are required in DetNet to provide a stable
        forwarding service and guarantee that the DetNet service is not impacted
        when the network topology changes. The following features are
        necessary in the control plane to implement explicit paths in DetNet:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Path computation: DetNet explicit paths need to meet the 
            Service Level Agreement (SLA) requirements of the application, which
            include bandwidth, maximum end-to-end delay, maximum end-to-end
            delay variation, maximum loss ratio, etc. In a distributed network
            system, an IGP with Constrained Shortest Path First (CSPF) may be
            used to compute a set of feasible paths for a DetNet service. In a
            centralized network system, the controller can compute paths
            satisfying the requirements of DetNet based on the network
            information collected from the DetNet domain.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Path establishment: The computed path for the DetNet service
            has to be sent/configured/signaled to the network device so that the
            corresponding DetNet flow can pass through the network domain
            following the specified path.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="resource-reservation" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Resource Reservation</name>
        <t>DetNet flows are supposed to be protected from congestion, so
        sufficient resource reservation for a DetNet service could protect
        a service from congestion. There are multiple types of resources in the
        network that could be allocated to DetNet flows, e.g., packet
        processing resources, buffer resources, and the bandwidth of the output
        port. The network resource requested by a specified DetNet service is
        determined by the SLA requirements and network capability.</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>Resource Allocation: Port bandwidth is one of the basic
            attributes of a network device that is easy to obtain or
            calculate. In current traffic engineering implementations, network
            resource allocation is synonymous with bandwidth allocation. A
            DetNet flow is characterized by a traffic specification, as
            defined in <xref target="RFC9016" format="default"/>, including attributes such as
            Interval, MaxPacketsPerInterval, and MaxPayloadSize.
            The traffic specification describes the worst case, rather than
            the average case, for the traffic to ensure that sufficient
            bandwidth and buffering resources are reserved to satisfy the
            traffic specification. However, in the case of DetNet, resource
            allocation is more than simple bandwidth reservation. For example,
            allocation of buffers and required queuing disciplines during
            forwarding may be required as well. Furthermore, resources must be
            ensured to execute DetNet service sub-layer functions on the node,
            such as protection and reordering through the use of PREOF.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Device configuration with or without flow discrimination: The
            resource allocation can be guaranteed by device configuration. For
            example, an output port bandwidth reservation can be configured as
            a parameter of queue management and the port scheduling algorithm.
            When DetNet flows are aggregated, a group of DetNet flows share
            the allocated resource in the network device. When the DetNet
            flows are treated independently, the device should maintain a
            mapping relationship between a DetNet flow and its corresponding
            resources.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section anchor="preof-support" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>PREOF Support</name>
        <t>DetNet path redundancy is supported via Packet Replication,
        Elimination, and Ordering Functions (PREOF). A DetNet
        flow is replicated and forwarded by multiple networks paths to avoid
        packet loss caused by device or link failures. In general, current
        control plane mechanisms that can be used to establish an explicit
        path, whether distributed or centralized, support point-to-point (P2P)
        and point-to-multipoint (P2MP) path establishment. PREOF requires the
        ability to compute and establish a set of multiple paths (e.g.,
        multiple Label Switched Path (LSP) segments in an MPLS network) from the point(s) of packet
        replication to the point(s) of packet merging and ordering. Mapping of
        DetNet flows or DetNet member flows to explicit path segments has to be ensured as
        well. Protocol extensions will be required to support these new
        features. Terminology will also be required to refer to this
        coordinated set of path segments (such as an "LSP graph"
        in the case of the DetNet MPLS data plane).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="dp-specific" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Data-Plane-Specific Considerations</name>
        <section anchor="legacy-mpls" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>DetNet in an MPLS Domain</name>
          <t>For the purposes of this document, "legacy MPLS"
          is defined as MPLS without the use of Segment Routing (see <xref target="SR" format="default"/> for a discussion of MPLS with Segment Routing) or
          MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) <xref target="RFC5960" format="default"/>.</t>
          <t>In legacy MPLS domains, a dynamic control plane using
          distributed signaling protocols is typically used for the
          distribution of MPLS labels used for forwarding MPLS packets.
  The dynamic signaling protocols most commonly used for label
  distribution are LDP <xref target="RFC5036"/>, RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC4875"/>, and BGP <xref target="RFC8277"/>
  (which enables BGP-based MPLS Layer 3 VPNs <xref target="RFC4384"/>, Layer 2 VPNs
  <xref target="RFC4664"/>, and EVPNs <xref target="RFC7432"/>).</t>

          <t>Any of these protocols could be used to distribute DetNet Service
          Labels (S-Labels) and Aggregation Labels (A-Labels) <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/>. As discussed in <xref target="RFC8938" format="default"/>,
          S-Labels are similar to other MPLS service labels, such as
          pseudowire and L3 VPN and L2 VPN labels, and could be distributed in a
          similar manner, such as through the use of targeted LDP or BGP. If
          these were to be used for DetNet, they would require extensions to
          support DetNet-specific features, such as PREOF, aggregation
          (A-Labels), node resource allocation, and queue placement.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="detnet-in-an-ip-domain" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>DetNet in an IP Domain</name>
	  <t>For the purposes of this document, "legacy IP" is defined as
	  IP without the use of Segment Routing (see <xref target="SR"
	  format="default"/> for a discussion of IP with Segment Routing).  It
	  should be noted that a DetNet IP data plane <xref target="RFC8939"/>
	  is simpler than a DetNet MPLS data plane <xref target="RFC8964"/>
	  and doesn't support PREOF, so only one path per flow or flow
	  aggregate is required. Therefore, possible protocol extensions are
	  expected to be limited, e.g., to existing IP routing protocols.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="SR" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>DetNet in a Segment Routing Domain</name>
          <t>Segment Routing <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/> is a scalable approach
          to building network domains that provides explicit routing via
          source routing encoded in packet headers, and it is combined with
          centralized network control to compute paths through the network.
          Forwarding paths are distributed with associated policies to network
          edge nodes for use in packet headers. Segment Routing reduces
          the amount of network signaling associated with distributed
          signaling protocols, such as RSVP-TE, and also reduces the amount of
          state in core nodes compared with that required for legacy MPLS
          and IP routing, as the state is now in the packets rather than in
          the routers. This could be useful for DetNet, where a very large
          number of flows through a network domain are expected, which would
          otherwise require the instantiation of state for each flow
          traversing each node in the network.</t>
          <t>Note that the DetNet MPLS and IP data planes described in <xref target="RFC8964" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8939" format="default"/> were constructed to
          be compatible with both types of Segment Routing: Segment Routing over MPLS (SR-MPLS) <xref target="RFC8660" format="default"/> and Segment Routing over IPv6 (SRv6) <xref target="RFC8754" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8986" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="encapsulation-support" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Encapsulation and Metadata Support</name>
        <t>To effectively manage DetNet flows, the controller plane will need to have a clear understanding of the encapsulation and metadata capabilities of the underlying network nodes. This will require a control mechanism that can discover, configure, and manage these parameters for each flow.</t>
        <t>The controller plane needs to understand and manage the encapsulation and metadata capabilities of the network nodes to provision DetNet flows effectively. This process might need a discovery phase in which the controller discovers which encapsulation types (e.g., MPLS, IP) and metadata schemes (e.g., sequencing, timestamping) that each node supports. After discovery, the controller might instruct nodes on the specific encapsulation and companion metadata to apply for a given flow. This ensures that DetNet packets are handled consistently across the network. For example, the controller might instruct a node to use an MPLS header and add a sequence number for a particular flow.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="management-plane-overview" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Management Plane Overview</name>
      <t>The management plane includes the ability to statically provision
      network nodes and to use Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (OAM) to monitor DetNet performance and to detect
      outages or other issues at the DetNet layer.</t>
      <section anchor="detnet-operations-administration-and-maintenance-oam" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>DetNet Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (OAM)</name>
        <t>This document covers the general considerations for OAM.</t>
        <section anchor="oam-for-performance-monitoring-pm" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>OAM for Performance Monitoring (PM)</name>
          <section anchor="active-pm" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Active PM</name>
            <t>Active PM is performed by injecting OAM packets into the
            network to estimate the performance of the network and by then measuring
            the performance of those OAM packets. Adding extra traffic can
            affect the delay and throughput performance of the network, and
            for this reason, Active PM is not recommended for use in
            operational DetNet domains. However, it is a useful test tool when
            commissioning a new network or during troubleshooting.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="passive-pm" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Passive PM</name>
            <t>Passive PM, such as In Situ Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (IOAM) <xref target="RFC9197" format="default"/>, monitors the actual service traffic in a network
            domain in order to measure its performance without having a
            detrimental effect on the network. As compared to Active PM,
            Passive PM is much preferred for use in DetNet domains.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="oam-for-connectivity-and-faultdefect-management-cfm" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>OAM for Connectivity and Fault Management (CFM)</name>
          <t>The detailed requirements for CFM
          in a DetNet IP domain and a DetNet MPLS domain
          are defined in <xref target="RFC9551" format="default"/>, <xref target="RFC9634" format="default"/>, and <xref target="RFC9546" format="default"/>, respectively.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Multi-Domain Aspects</name>
      <t>When there are multiple domains involved, multiple Controller Plane
      Functions (CPFs) would have to collaborate to implement the requests
      received from the Flow Management Entity (FME) <xref target="RFC8655"/>
      as per-flow, per-hop behaviors installed in the DetNet nodes for each
      individual flow.  Adding multi-domain support might require some support
      at the CPF. For example, CPFs of different domains, e.g., PCEs, need to
      discover each other and then authenticate and negotiate per-hop
      behaviors. Furthermore, in the case of wireless domains,
      per-domain functions specific to Reliable and Available Wireless (RAW) <xref target="I-D.ietf-raw-architecture" format="default"/>, such as Point of Local Repairs (PLRs), have to also be
      considered, e.g., in addition to the PCEs. Depending on the multi-domain
      support provided by the application plane, the controller plane might be
      relieved from some responsibilities (e.g., if the application plane
      takes care of splitting what needs to be provided by each domain).</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document provides a framework for the DetNet Controller Plane
      and does not include any protocol specifications. Any future
      specification that is defined to support the DetNet Controller Plane is
      expected to include the appropriate security considerations. For overall
      security considerations of DetNet, see <xref target="RFC8655" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC9055" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-raw-architecture" to="RAW-ARCH"/>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8655.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8938.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9055.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9016.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9551.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9634.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9546.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8964.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8939.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9056.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9025.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9037.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9023.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9024.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9320.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9633.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8754.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6020.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7426.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5960.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8283.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4384.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8277.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5036.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7432.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8660.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9552.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4875.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4664.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8986.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9197.xml"/>

<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-raw-architecture" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-raw-architecture-30">
   <front>
      <title>Reliable and Available Wireless Architecture</title>
      <author initials="P." surname="Thubert" fullname="Pascal Thubert" role="editor">
         <organization>Without Affiliation</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="July" day="25" year="2025" />
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-raw-architecture-30" />
   
</reference>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6632.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7950.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="acknowledgments" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>Thanks to <contact fullname="Jim Guichard"/>, <contact
      fullname="Donald Eastlake 3rd"/>, and <contact fullname="Stewart Bryant"/>
      for their reviews and comments.</t>
      <t>The authors would also like to thank <contact fullname="Deb Cooley"/>,
      <contact fullname="Mike Bishop"/>, <contact fullname="Mohamed
      Boucadair"/>, <contact fullname="Gorry Fairhurst"/>, and <contact
      fullname="Dave Thaler"/> for their comments during the different
      directorate and IESG reviews.</t>
    </section>

    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>

      <contact fullname="Fengwei Qin">
	<organization>China Mobile</organization>
	<address>
	  <email>qinfengwei@chinamobile.com</email>
	</address>
      </contact>

    </section>


  </back>


</rfc>
